A good AI answer can still arrive too
early.
You ask a question. The model gives a
fluent paragraph, a clean plan, maybe
even a reasonable recommendation.
It feels like progress. But sometimes the
answer is solving a question you
have not finished asking. This video is
about slowing the first answer down
just enough to keep the human parts of the
decision visible.
By the end, you will have one prompt you
can reuse before any important AI
answer. It checks three things: Goal.
Evidence.
Ownership.
What are we trying to do? What facts would
change the answer?
And what parts are still mine to choose?
Think of the model as a bright worktable.
It can lay out options and tradeoffs.
But the worktable should not decide what
the work is for.
Start with a small example.
You ask: Should I redesign this onboarding
page?
The model might say: simplify the page,
reduce friction, test a clearer button.
Useful, maybe.
But it is answering a half-built question.
Does better mean more signups, fewer
confused users, fewer support tickets,
or a more honest first impression?
Those are different goals. If you do not
name the goal, the model may quietly
name it for you. So the first checkpoint
is Goal: what am I actually trying
to decide or create? Not just make this
better.
Better for whom?
Better by what measure? Better at what
cost?
This applies beyond product work: a
purchase, a job choice, a family plan,
a hard email.
Once the target is visible, the model can
help without inventing the game.
The second checkpoint is Evidence.
Ask: what real-world facts would change
the answer?
If the model recommends a redesign, what
would make that recommendation stronger
or weaker? Maybe users drop off at the
second step.
Maybe support tickets mention the same
confusing sentence.
Maybe people hesitate over a price detail.
Or maybe the page is not the real problem.
So instead of only asking, explain your
reasoning, try asking: What evidence
would change your recommendation?
Separate what you know from what you are
assuming.
That turns the answer into a checklist for
reality.
This is a small habit, not a safety
guarantee.
Here is the honest warning: people can
lean too hard on automated recommendations,
and a clear explanation does not
automatically make reliance appropriate.
So the point is not: ask for an
explanation and relax.
The point is: make the goal, evidence,
assumptions, and value choices visible
before the advice feels settled.
The third checkpoint is Ownership.
Some parts of a decision are not facts the
model can discover.
They depend on values, context,
responsibility, and risk.
Suppose you write: Draft an email telling
a collaborator I am unhappy that
the timeline is slipping. The model can
produce a polished email.
But it does not know what you want to
protect.
Is the email for repairing trust, setting
a boundary, getting a new date, or
documenting accountability?
Those goals can lead to different wording.
Same facts.
Different posture.
Different risk.
A gentle version might ask, Could we
revisit the timeline?
A direct version might say, I need a new
date by Friday.
A firm version might say, I cannot commit
to the next milestone without a new
date. The model can show these options
side by side.
But you choose the posture, the risk, and
the line you are willing to stand
behind.
A better request is: Before drafting, list
the possible goals of this message
and the relationship risks of each.
Then give three versions: gentle, direct,
and firm.
Separate tone choices from factual claims.
Now the model is doing work on the table.
Options are useful.
Ownership is not optional.
You are still responsible for the
decision.
Here is the whole habit as one prompt:
Before answering, help me keep ownership
of this decision.
1. Restate the goal you think I am
pursuing.
2. List the facts or evidence that would
change your answer.
3. Identify which parts depend on my
values, context, or risk tolerance.
Then give advice, separating assumptions
from recommendations.
That does not make the model correct.
But it gives you three places to
intervene.
If the goal is wrong, correct it.
If the evidence is missing, lower your
confidence or go find it.
If the answer depends on values, stop
pretending it is only a technical question.
Try it on the next AI request that
actually matters.
Paste the prompt before your question.
Let the model fill in the goal, the
evidence, and the value-dependent parts.
Then edit those three answers before you
accept the recommendation.
Wrong goal?
Fix it. Missing evidence?
Look for it or lower your confidence.
Value tradeoff?
Pause. Smooth prose cannot choose that for
you.
That is the difference between using AI to
think with you and letting it quietly
finish the thinking for you.
The point is not to think alone.
A good model can widen the table: more
options, clearer tradeoffs, sharper
questions, and a second pass on your
reasoning.
Use it for that. Delegate the spread of
options.
Delegate the first draft.
Delegate the list of assumptions you might
have missed.
But keep the purpose, the evidence
standard, the risk tolerance, and the final
judgment with you.
Before you accept the answer, ask: What is
the goal?
What evidence would change this?
What belongs to me to choose?
Let the model widen the table.
Keep your hands on the question.