A good AI answer can still arrive too early.
You ask a question.
The model gives you a fluent paragraph, a clean plan, maybe even a reasonable
recommendation.
It feels like progress.
But sometimes the answer is solving a question you have not actually chosen yet.
By the end of this video, you will have a prompt you can reuse
before any important AI answer.
It checks three things: **Goal.
Grounding.
Ownership.** What are we trying to do?
What facts would change the answer?
And what parts are still mine to choose?
Think of the model as a bright worktable.
It can lay out options, tradeoffs, and missing questions.
But the worktable should not decide what the work is for.
Here is a simple fictional example.
You ask: Should I redesign my onboarding page?
The model might answer instantly: simplify the page, reduce friction, emphasize the main benefit,
add social proof, test a clearer button.
That advice might be useful.
It is also answering a half-built question.
Does “better” mean more signups?
Fewer confused users?
Fewer support tickets?
A more honest first impression?
A clearer explanation of who the product is not for?
Those are different goals.
If you do not name the goal, the model may quietly name it for
you.
The first checkpoint is **Goal**.
Before asking for advice, ask: what am I actually trying to decide or create?
Not just “make this better.” Better for whom?
Better by what measure?
Better at what cost?
A stronger version of the prompt might be: I am deciding whether to redesign
an onboarding page.
The goal is not just more signups.
It is more new users who understand the product and are less likely to
need support in the first week.
Now the model has a scoreboard.
It can still help, but it is not inventing the game.
The second checkpoint is **Grounding**.
Ask: what real-world facts would change the answer?
If the model recommends a redesign, what would make that recommendation stronger or weaker?
Maybe users drop off at the second step.
Maybe support tickets keep mentioning the same confusing sentence.
Maybe recordings show people hesitating over a price detail.
Or maybe the page is not the real problem at all.
So instead of only asking, “explain your reasoning,” try asking: What evidence would change
your recommendation?
Separate what you know from what you are assuming.
That turns the answer into a checklist for reality.
This matters because the goal is not to avoid AI help.
The goal is to rely on it in the right place.
Researchers studying decision support often use terms like automation bias or over-reliance for cases
where people lean too hard on automated recommendations.
And in human-AI decision studies, even explanations can change how people rely on a
system without reliably making them better at telling which recommendations are correct.
So this prompt is not a magic fix.
It does not prove the answer is right.
It does something smaller: it keeps the goal, the evidence, and the human tradeoffs
visible before the advice becomes too easy to accept.
The third checkpoint is **Ownership**.
Some parts of a decision are not facts the model can discover.
They depend on values, context, responsibility, and risk.
For the onboarding page, maybe a shorter version increases signups but gives people a
less accurate expectation.
Maybe a clearer page filters out some users but creates more trust.
A model can describe that tradeoff.
It cannot decide what kind of relationship you want with users.
The same idea shows up in a more everyday example.
Suppose you write: Draft an email telling a collaborator I am unhappy that the
timeline is slipping.
The model can produce a polished email.
But it does not know what you want to protect.
Do you want to repair trust?
Set a boundary?
Get a new date?
Document accountability?
Lower the temperature?
Make the seriousness impossible to miss?
Those are different choices.
The model can show versions.
You choose what you are willing to stand behind.
A better request is: Before drafting, list the possible goals of this message and
the relationship risks of each.
Then give three versions: gentle, direct, and firm.
Separate tone choices from factual claims.
Now the model is doing work on the table.
You are still responsible for the decision.
Here is the whole habit as one prompt: Before answering, help me keep ownership
of this decision.
1.
Restate the goal you think I am pursuing.
2.
List the facts or evidence that would change your answer.
3.
Identify which parts depend on my values, context, or risk tolerance.
Then give advice, separating assumptions from recommendations.
That does not make the model correct.
But it gives you three places to intervene.
If the goal is wrong, correct it.
If the evidence is missing, go look for it.
If the answer depends on values, stop pretending it is only a technical question.
The point is not to think alone.
A good model can widen the room: more options, clearer tradeoffs, sharper questions, and
a second pass on your reasoning.
Use it for that.
Use the model for options and tradeoffs.
Keep the goal, evidence, and final judgment visible.
Before you accept the answer, ask: What is the goal?
What would ground this in reality?
What belongs to me to choose?
Let the AI help you see more.
Do not let it decide what seeing is for.