A good AI answer can still arrive too
early.
You ask a question. The model gives a
fluent paragraph, a clean plan, maybe
even a reasonable recommendation.
It feels like progress. But sometimes the
answer is solving a question you
have not finished asking. This video is
about slowing the first answer down
just enough to keep the human parts of the
decision visible.
By the end, you will have one prompt you
can reuse before any important AI
answer. It checks three things: Goal.
Grounding. Ownership.
What are we trying to do? What facts would
change the answer?
And what parts are still mine to choose?
Think of the model as a bright worktable.
It can lay out options and tradeoffs.
But the worktable should not decide what
the work is for.
Start with a small example.
You ask: Should I redesign this onboarding
page?
The model might say: simplify the page,
reduce friction, test a clearer button.
Useful, maybe.
But it is answering a half-built question.
Does better mean more signups, fewer
confused users, fewer support tickets,
or a more honest first impression?
Those are different goals. If you do not
name the goal, the model may quietly
name it for you.
So the first checkpoint is Goal: what am I
actually trying to decide or create?
Not just make this better. Better for
whom?
Better by what measure? Better at what
cost?
This applies beyond product work: a
purchase, a job choice, a family plan,
a hard email.
Once the target is visible, the model can
help without inventing the game.
The second checkpoint is Grounding.
Ask: what real-world facts would change
the answer?
If the model recommends a redesign, what
would make that recommendation stronger
or weaker?
Maybe users drop off at the second step.
Maybe support tickets mention the same
confusing sentence.
Maybe people hesitate over a price detail.
Or maybe the page is not the real problem.
So instead of only asking, explain your
reasoning, try asking: What evidence
would change your recommendation?
Separate what you know from what you are
assuming.
That turns the answer into a checklist for
reality.
This is a small habit, not a safety
guarantee.
Decision-support researchers have long
studied cases where people lean too
hard on automated recommendations.
In some human-AI studies, explanations
changed how people relied on a system.
They did not reliably help people spot
which recommendations were correct.
So the point is not: ask for an
explanation and relax.
The point is: make the goal, assumptions,
evidence, and value choices visible
before the advice feels settled.
The third checkpoint is Ownership.
Some parts of a decision are not facts the
model can discover.
They depend on values, context,
responsibility, and risk.
Suppose you write: Draft an email telling
a collaborator I am unhappy that
the timeline is slipping. The model can
produce a polished email.
But it does not know what you want to
protect.
Do you want to repair trust, set a boundary,
get a new date, or document accountability?
A gentle version may preserve warmth but
blur the boundary.
A firm version may create clarity but
raise the temperature.
A direct version may do both.
The model can show versions side by side.
You choose what you are willing to stand
behind.
A better request is: Before drafting, list
the possible goals of this message
and the relationship risks of each.
Then give three versions: gentle, direct,
and firm.
Separate tone choices from factual claims.
Now the model is doing work on the table.
You are still responsible for the
decision.
Here is the whole habit as one prompt:
Before answering, help me keep ownership
of this decision.
1. Restate the goal you think I am
pursuing.
2. List the facts or evidence that would
change your answer.
3. Identify which parts depend on my
values, context, or risk tolerance.
Then give advice, separating assumptions
from recommendations.
That does not make the model correct.
But it gives you three places to
intervene.
If the goal is wrong, correct it.
If the evidence is missing, go look for
it.
If the answer depends on values, stop
pretending it is only a technical question.
Try it on the next AI request that
actually matters.
Paste the prompt before your question.
Let the model fill in the goal, the
evidence, and the value-dependent parts.
Then edit those three answers before you
accept the recommendation.
Wrong goal?
Fix it. Missing evidence?
Look for it or lower your confidence.
Value tradeoff?
Pause. Smooth prose cannot choose that for
you.
That is the difference between using AI to
think with you and letting it quietly
finish the thinking for you.
The point is not to think alone.
A good model can widen the room: more
options, clearer tradeoffs, sharper questions,
and a second pass on your reasoning.
Use it for that. Use the model for options
and tradeoffs.
Keep the goal, evidence, and final
judgment visible.
Before you accept the answer, ask: What is
the goal?
What would ground this in reality?
What belongs to me to choose?
Let the AI help you see more.
Do not let it decide what seeing is for.