Imagine two answers in a review queue.
One is excellent. It is clear, complete, and already near
the top of the scale.
The other is shaky. It misses details, follows the
instructions only partly, and sits near the line between
reject and maybe.
Now add a label.
Not a real change to the answer. Just a displayed name. A
model name. A team name. A school name. A vendor name.
Some cue the judge is not supposed to use.
If that label creates bias, many people picture a simple
bonus: plus half a point for the favored label,
everywhere.
But a more dangerous pattern can look different.
The strong answer has nowhere to go. It was already high.
The weak answer has room to be forgiven.
So the label does not lift the whole scale evenly. It
raises the floor.
This is the bias that looks like mercy.
In the AI Village label-swap study, the same answers were
shown under different displayed author labels.
That lets you ask a causal question: same work, different
label, different score?
The answer was not the same for every judge. Gemini showed
the clearest displayed-self-label boost. GPT-5.5 was
exactly label-invariant in the paired slice.
Claude and Kimi were smaller or noisier in this particular
test.
But where label effects appeared, they often had an
important shape.
The boost was not just a flat reward for the label. It was
larger on lower-scoring answers.
A weak answer under a favorable label could get more
benefit of the doubt. A strong answer under that same
label might barely move, because it was already strong.
That matters because real decisions often happen near
thresholds.
If a score moves from 9.1 to 9.3, nothing may change.
If a score moves from 5.8 to 6.2, the answer may cross
from fail to pass, reject to review, unsafe to maybe safe,
or below the leaderboard cutoff to above
it.
A small average effect can hide a big decision effect.
This is why “the average label bias is only small” is not
enough comfort.
Ask where the movement happens.
Does it happen on borderline examples?
Does it happen on weaker work?
Does it happen in one task, language, model family, or
difficulty slice?
Does it change pass-fail decisions, or only move scores
far from any action boundary?
A floor-raiser pattern also changes how you audit an AI
judge.
Do not test only polished examples. Include messy,
mediocre, and borderline examples.
Do not report only the mean score difference. Plot the
label effect against the baseline score.
Do not ask only whether the judge is biased. Ask which
decisions the bias can change.
And if labels are not supposed to matter, remove them
before scoring. Or at least run a paired label-swap audit
before trusting the scores.
There is one more caution.
Calling this mercy is a metaphor, not a mind-reading
claim. The model is not necessarily feeling sympathy. It
is producing scores under prompts, labels, and learned
patterns.
But the operational effect can still look like mercy: weak
work gets softened when a favorable cue is present.
For humans, the lesson is simple.
Bias is not only about who gets the biggest average bonus.
Bias is also about who gets rescued at the line.
When an AI judge is part of a real decision, inspect the
floor, inspect the threshold, and inspect the examples
that almost changed.