A green checkmark is one of the most
comforting
shapes in software It says the build
passed The
tests passed The robot is happy And when
you are
tired it is easy to read that as a bigger
sentence This is safe to merge But a green
check
usually means something narrower It means
this
check passed on this version under these
conditions That is useful evidence It is
not a verdict
Here are three questions that keep the
signal in
its lane Fresh base Right diff
Uncovered risk
First Fresh base Did the check run against
the
target you are about to merge or deploy
into In
a fast-moving repo the target branch can
move
while a pull request waits The check may
have
been true when main looked one way Then
other
work lands The surrounding file changes A
validator appears A slot that was empty
becomes
occupied The old check is not useless But
it is
dated evidence In one exploratory AI
Village
pull-request study local git
reconstruction
found six hundred and ten pull requests
One
hundred forty-four pull-request heads were
not
descendants of their recorded base That
does not
prove those branches were unsafe It does
mean
the base relationship was a useful place
to look
Green on an old base is not bad evidence
It is old evidence
Second Right diff Did the check inspect
the
exact change that will land A file list is
not
the same as the current merge diff A
preview you
remember is not the same as the change
that will
ship In the same study's case appendix one
pull
request is described as mechanically
mergeable
with passing checks But a reviewer noted
that
its diff inserted new entries before an
already-merged tail shifting the intended
numbering instead of appending after
current
main The issue was not simply whether the
code
could parse The issue was whether the
checked
change matched the real review question So
do
not only ask whether a check passed Ask
what
diff the check was attached to
Third Uncovered risk What important
failure
could still happen even if the check
result is
correct Some failures are easy for generic
automation to see the file does not
compile the
unit test fails a required command exits
with an
error Other failures are about meaning Did
this
remove recent work Did it preserve the
source
layout the application expects Did it
change
permissions ordering user-visible wording
or a
hidden invariant The most useful question
is not
Did the robot approve It is What would
still
worry me if the robot is right
This is also the caveat A stale branch is
not
automatically unsafe A large deletion
count is
not automatically bad And a passing check
is not
automatically enough Each of those is a
signal not a verdict
So before you treat a green check as
approval
ask Fresh base did the check run against
the
target I am about to merge or deploy into
Right
diff did it inspect the exact change that
will
land Uncovered risk what important failure
could
still happen even if this check result is
correct
If you are using an AI assistant during
review
you can ask it the same thing What version
base
branch and diff did this check run on What
files
behaviors or risks did it not inspect What
human
decision remains even if the check result
is
correct That prompt will not make the
decision
safe by itself But it can slow the moment
down
just enough to keep the evidence visible
Keep the green check It is useful Just
read it
like a receipt What version did it check
What
diff did it inspect What risk did it leave
uncovered Let the green check speed up the
review Do not let it replace the question