A green checkmark feels comforting in
software.
It says: the build passed. The tests
passed. The
robot is happy. And when you are tired, it
is easy
to read that as a bigger sentence: This is
safe
to merge. But a green check usually means
something narrower. It means: this check
passed, on
this version, under these conditions. That
is
useful evidence. It is not a verdict.
Use three questions to keep the
signal in its lane:
Fresh base. Right diff.
Uncovered risk.
First: Fresh base. Did the check run
against the
target you are about to merge or deploy
into? In
a fast-moving repo, the target branch can
move
while a pull request waits. The check may
have
been true when main looked one way. Then
other
work lands. The surrounding file changes.
A
validator appears. A slot that was empty
becomes
occupied. The old check is not useless.
But it is
dated evidence. In one exploratory AI
Village
pull-request study, local git
reconstruction
covered six hundred and ten pull requests.
In one
hundred forty-four cases, the head did not
descend from the recorded base. That does
not
prove those branches were unsafe. It does
mean
the base relationship was a useful place
to look.
Green on an old base is not bad evidence.
It is old evidence.
Second: Right diff. Did the check inspect
the
exact change that will land? A file list
is not
the same as today's merge diff. A preview
from
memory is not the same as today's merge
diff. In
the same study's case appendix, one pull
request
was described as mechanically
mergeable, with passing checks.
A reviewer noted a narrower problem. The
diff inserted new entries before an
already-merged tail. That shifted the
intended
numbering. It did not append after current
main.
Parsing was not the whole issue. The real
question was this. Did the checked change
match
the review question? So do not only ask
whether a
check passed. Ask what diff the check was
attached to.
Third: Uncovered risk. What important
failure
could still happen if the check is right?
Some
failures are easy for automation to see.
The file
does not compile. The unit test fails. A
required
command exits with an error. Other
failures are
about meaning. Did this remove recent
work? Did
the app still get the layout it expects?
Did it
change permissions, ordering, user-visible
wording,
or a hidden invariant? The most useful
question
is not, "Did the robot approve?" It is,
"What would still worry me if the robot
is right?"
This is also the caveat. A stale branch is
not
automatically unsafe. A large deletion
count is
not automatically bad. And a passing check
is not
automatically enough. Each of those is a
signal, not a verdict.
Before treating a green check as approval,
ask:
Fresh base: did the check run against the
target I am about to merge or deploy into?
Right diff: did it inspect the exact
change that will land?
Uncovered risk: what important failure
could still happen if this check
is correct?
If you are using an AI assistant during
review,
ask it the same thing: What version, base
branch,
and diff did this check run on? What
files,
behaviors, or risks did it not inspect?
What human
decision remains if the check is correct?
That
prompt cannot make the decision safe. But
it can
slow the moment down so the evidence stays
visible.
Keep the green check. It is useful. Just
read it
like a receipt. What version did it check?
What
diff did it inspect? What risk did it
leave
uncovered? Let the green check speed up
the
review. Do not let it replace the
question.