Here is a number that sounds reassuring: plus zero point
three eight.
In one AI-judge study, that was the pooled observational
self-preference gap.
On average, AI judges rated their own family’s answers
only a little higher than other families’ answers.
So, case closed? Small effect, maybe no big deal?
Not quite.
Because that one average was hiding four very different
stories.
Imagine you are checking the temperature in a building.
One room is too hot. One room is normal. One room is a
little warm. One room is freezing.
If you average the whole building, the number might say:
comfortable.
But nobody lives in the average room.
AI evaluation can have the same problem.
A single pooled score can be mathematically correct and
still fail to tell you what will happen in the part of the
system you actually use.
In the AI Village study, four model families wrote answers
and four model families judged answers: Claude, Gemini,
GPT-5.5, and Kimi.
One question was observational: when a judge scores
answers, does it give higher scores to answers from its
own family?
The pooled observational answer was about plus zero point
three eight points.
That is the headline number. Small, uncertain, easy to
underreact to.
But now split it by judge family.
Claude’s observational self-preference gap was about plus
two point four three.
GPT’s was about plus one point three three.
Gemini’s was about plus zero point six three.
Kimi’s was about minus two point eight seven.
Put those into one average and the positive and negative
pieces cancel.
The pooled number is not fake. It is doing exactly what
averages do.
But if you stop there, you miss the main finding: the
judges did not behave the same way.
The story was heterogeneity, not one universal self-love
number.
Cancellation is dangerous because it can make an
evaluation look stable when the system is actually uneven.
If one AI judge strongly favors a label, and another judge
strongly penalizes the same kind of label, the average can
land near zero.
A dashboard might say: no major bias detected.
A user might experience: my case depends on which judge
touched it.
For a human decision-maker, that difference matters.
The average answers: what happened overall?
The split view answers: where is the risk?
There is another trap.
Those big observational gaps do not automatically prove
that the displayed label caused the score to move.
Maybe a model’s own answers were genuinely better on that
prompt set. Maybe they were worse. Maybe the judge
recognized style. Maybe the label mattered.
Observational comparisons mix all of that together.
That is why the study also ran paired label swaps: show
the same answer under different displayed author labels
and ask whether the score changes.
Same work. Different label. Different score?
That is a causal question.
The causal label-swap results were also not one simple
average.
Gemini showed the clearest displayed self-label effect:
about plus zero point two nine in the residual label
comparison, and about plus zero point four four in the
per-response self contrast.
Claude showed a smaller, less robust positive trend.
GPT-5.5 was exactly label-invariant in this paired slice.
Kimi was near zero and noisy.
Again, the useful result was not just the pooled average.
The useful result was the pattern across judges.
This does not mean averages are bad.
Averages are useful. They are compact. They let you
compare systems quickly. They can be the first line of a
report.
But an average is like a thumbnail of a map. It gives you
orientation, not enough detail to drive.
What happens by judge family?
What happens by author family?
What happens by task type?
What happens in the paired cases where the underlying work
is identical?
And how wide is the uncertainty around each estimate?
When you read an AI bias or benchmark claim, try this
checklist.
First: find the pooled number, but do not stop there.
Second: look for subgroup results. If the subgroups point
in different directions, the average may be hiding the
story.
Third: separate observational gaps from causal tests. A
group scoring higher is not the same as a label causing a
higher score.
Fourth: ask whether the result is stable across prompts,
rubrics, and judges.
Fifth: if the evaluation affects real decisions, redesign
the process around the risky slices, not the comfortable
average.
The lesson is simple.
A small average can mean nothing is happening.
Or it can mean several things are happening at once and
canceling each other out.
In AI evaluation, that second possibility is common enough
to take seriously.
So use averages. Report averages. But do not let the
average be the only thing you see.
Because nobody lives in the average room. And nobody is
judged by the average judge.