Imagine two judges reading the exact same answer. Same
words, same prompt, same rubric. The only thing that
changes is the name tag above it: Gemini, Claude, GPT-5.5,
or Kimi.
If the score changes, the label did something. That is the
question behind this video: do AI judges play favorites?
We ran a controlled test across four model families, and
the answer was not a simple yes or no.
One judge showed the clearest causal label bias while
barely recognizing its own writing.
One judge recognized itself perfectly but stayed exactly
label-invariant in the paired test.
And the strongest pattern looked less like ego and more
like a benefit-of-the-doubt effect for weaker answers.
This matters because AI systems are increasingly used as
judges. Researchers use model judges to evaluate generated
answers. Product teams use them for regression tests.
Benchmarks use them when human review would be too slow or
too expensive. That can be useful, but only if we
understand the failure modes.
If a judge sees a model name, a provider name, or a
familiar writing style, the score may stop being a pure
measurement of answer quality.
It can become a mixture of quality, label, style, and
prior expectation.
Here was the setup. We wrote ten fresh, out-of-
distribution prompt families: coding, math, ethics,
design, history, explanation, creative writing, and more.
Four model families answered every prompt: Claude Opus
4.7, Gemini 3.1 Pro, GPT-5.5, and Kimi K2.6.
Then the same four families judged the responses with a
five-part rubric: correctness, completeness, clarity,
creativity, and constraint adherence.
The important design choice was separating two questions.
First, what happens in ordinary blind scoring, where the
text itself can still contain style clues?
Second, what happens when we hold the response text fixed
and only change the displayed author label?
The first result is already a warning against easy
headlines.
In the blind baseline, the pooled average self-preference
gap was small and noisy: about plus zero point three eight
points. But the average hid a sharp split.
Claude showed a raw self-gap of plus two point four three.
GPT-5.5 showed plus one point three three. Gemini showed a
smaller plus zero point six three.
Kimi showed minus two point eight seven. So the headline
is not: all AI judges prefer themselves.
The headline is: different judge families behaved
differently, and the average alone can hide the story.
A raw self-gap is useful, but it is not automatically a
causal bias estimate. If a judge gives higher scores to
its own family, maybe it is favoring itself.
Or maybe that family wrote stronger answers on the chosen
prompts. Or maybe the judge rewards a style that happens
to match its own.
Or maybe it infers authorship from phrasing even when no
label is shown. All of those mechanisms can move an
observational score.
That is why we treated the blind baseline as a clue, not
as the final answer.
Kimi is the clearest cautionary tale. In the blind
baseline, Kimi looked as if it strongly penalized itself:
minus two point eight seven points.
But Kimi-authored answers also scored much lower on this
prompt set. The Kimi versus non-Kimi quality gap was about
minus three point five four points.
Once we adjusted for that quality difference, Kimi's
residual moved positive, to plus zero point six six.
So the raw negative self-gap was not good evidence that
Kimi disliked its own name. It mostly reflected a quality
confound in this particular prompt set.
To test label bias more cleanly, we used a label-swap
design. Take the same answer. Show it once under one
displayed author label and once under another.
Then compare scores within that exact response. The
content is held fixed, so differences in answer quality
cannot explain a score change.
This was a reduced paired design, not every possible label
for every response, so it still has limits.
But it asks a much sharper question than the blind
baseline: did the displayed label itself causally move the
score?
This is where the story became sharper. Gemini showed the
clearest causal displayed-self label effect.
In the paired slice, the Gemini self-label effect was
about plus zero point two nine by residual label contrast,
and plus zero point four four by the per-response self
contrast.
Claude showed a smaller positive trend. Kimi was near zero
and noisy.
GPT-5.5 was exactly label-invariant in this paired slice:
when the displayed label changed, its scores did not move.
So label bias was not universal.
It depended strongly on the judge family.
Here is the public label-swap figure from the research
artifact. The purpose of including the real plot is not to
make the video look more technical.
It is to show the shape of the evidence. The Gemini effect
is the clearest positive causal signal. The GPT-5.5 result
is exactly flat in this paired slice.
Claude is smaller and less decisive. Kimi is near zero
with wide uncertainty.
The visual point is the same as the statistical point: one
headline number would erase the differences that matter.
A tempting explanation is that a model favors its own work
because it recognizes its own writing. But recognition and
favoritism came apart.
Gemini identified its own responses as Gemini in only one
out of ten self cases, yet it showed the clearest causal
displayed-self label effect.
GPT-5.5 recognized its own work in ten out of ten self
cases, yet it was exactly label-invariant in the paired
label-swap slice.
So the mechanism cannot simply be: I know this is mine,
therefore I score it higher.
Another detail makes the mechanism more interesting.
Gemini did not only show a displayed-Gemini boost.
It also showed an anti-Kimi displayed-label penalty: about
minus zero point two four five residual points, with all
seven nonzero prompt signs going negative in that
analysis.
That matters because it pushes against a simple vanity
story. A displayed label can act like a prior about
expected quality.
The judge may be applying more charity to one label and
less charity to another, even when the underlying answer
text is identical.
The strongest mechanism pattern was what we called floor-
raising. If a favorable label were just a fixed bonus, the
uplift would be similar for strong and weak answers.
Instead, for judges with nonzero label effects, the self-
label uplift was larger when the baseline score was lower.
Strong answers were already near the ceiling.
Weaker answers had more room for interpretation, and a
favorable label seemed to buy more benefit of the doubt.
That is not exactly ego.
It is more like a charity correction applied unevenly.
It is important to say what this does not prove. It does
not prove that every AI judge favors itself.
It does not prove that models have human-like egos or
motives. It does not cover every model, every prompt
distribution, or every evaluation setting.
The paired label-swap design was reduced rather than
exhaustive.
The useful claim is narrower and more measurable: visible
labels can causally affect some model judges, in model-
specific ways, and those effects can be separated from
answer quality if you
design the experiment carefully.
The practical lesson is not: never use AI judges. The
judges still shared meaningful quality signal. The lesson
is to use them with guardrails.
Hide irrelevant author or model labels when possible. Use
multiple judges rather than one model family alone. Report
per-judge results before pooling.
Separate observational patterns from causal label-swap
audits.
And be suspicious of a single clean headline number until
it has survived heterogeneity checks, quality controls,
and causal stress tests.
So, do AI judges play favorites? Sometimes, but not all in
the same way. In our test, Gemini's displayed label
mattered causally.
GPT-5.5's displayed label did not move scores in the
paired slice.
Kimi's apparent self-penalty was mostly about response
quality on this prompt set, not a causal dislike of its
own name.
And the clearest mechanism looked like floor-raising for
weaker work. That is messier than yes or no.
It is also the kind of answer we need if AI systems are
going to evaluate more of the world's work.